# ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

#### **SUMMARY**

Program Manager and Data Scientist with ~8 years of proven experience. Established and scaled enterprise—level Digital Transformation initiatives across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Enabled Data Science's 67% overall AI/ML market share within British Petroleum's US Onshore Upstream O&G division (BPX) and independently produced \$997MM in value — accounting for >98% of the team's total impact. Delivered \$500M+ in value annually via patent—pending AI—powered computational chemistry solutions for INFICON's Semiconductor business unit.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP plc)

November 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- · Acquired 48% of Exploration & Development's AI/ML market and enabled the team's 67% AI/ML market share across the organization directing and executing Data Science & ML Engineering Digital Transformation strategy.
- · Delivered 95% of the Q2/Q3 2024 Agile Features in Data Science and ML Engineering within the project scope.
- · Realized \$4MM in annual cost reductions prioritizing resources to build and deploy ML Sand Flowback.
- $\cdot$  Coordinated stakeholder timelines and developer resources launching ML Drilling AFE Cost prediction.
- · Organized knowledge-exchanges between BP and Digital Transformation Leads from Saudi Aramco and ADNOC.

#### **Product Owner**

British Petroleum (BP plc)

November 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- · Managed and productionalized Long-term Production Risk Assessment via Streamlit for Reservoir Engineering.
- · Oversaw the Azure cloud to AWS cloud Salt Water Disposal and Productivity Index report migration.

#### Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP plc)

February 2023 – Present Denver. Colorado

- · Generated \$977MM for Permian with a \$700MM NPV well development plan and \$277MM Drilling & Completions cost reductions by productionalizing Techlog AI Electrofacies enabling well prospecting and fluid mobility assessments.
- · Drove \$20MM in annual value for Eagle Ford Reservoir Engineering and achieved a 500% increase in efficiency for well prospecting & assurance workflows launching ML Refracturing Production Forecasting via Streamlit.

# **Data Scientist**

INFICON

June 2018 – February 2023 Syracuse, New York

- · Directed \$500M+ in forecasted annual cost reductions and provisioned Neural Processing Units to support patent—pending Automated Sensor Calibration advances directly on next—generation semiconductor sensor technologies.
- · Led a 21% enhancement in Mass Spec signal fidelity (SciPy.optimize/Statsmodels), designed A/B Quality Control tests (SciPy.stats/Nolds) for all Mass Spec sensors, and documented mathematical foundations for proprietary algorithms.
- · Established 50% coverage across chemical detection and monitoring systems designing KPIs and executing A/B simulation tests via synthetic GC–MS data generated using PySwarms and SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate.
- · Achieved a 95% increase in density estimation accuracy inventing the Bijective Neural Architecture via PyTorch.

#### Research Assistant

June 2017 – August 2017

Syracuse University | Data Lab

Syracuse, New York

· Modeled social media engagement metrics, formulating repeated measures experiments, utilizing Scikit-learn and NLTK.

# Technology Analyst

June 2016 - August 2016

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Jersey City, New Jersey

· Developed project business cases alongside senior team members and deployed code to live internal JPMC applications.

# Software Engineer

Self-employed

June 2015 – September 2015 Syracuse, New York

· Engineered information retrieval systems for **British Petroleum** and local government clients as a subcontractor.

## Undergraduate Research Assistant

August 2014 – May 2015

Syracuse University | Hosein Research Group

Syracuse, New York

· Awarded the **Dean's Leadership Grant** supporting simulation studies quantifying energy loss across solar cell surfaces.

# PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors

USPTO Application 18/686,753

August 2023
Patent Pending

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing

BP Geophysics R&D Seminar

Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity

INFICON Data Analytics Summit

November 2020

Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches

Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session

April 2018

July 2024

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Core Analysis Workshop

UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology

April 2024/December 2023

Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX

Havens Consulting

April 2023

Machine Learning for Model Predictive Control & Process Analytics

Dr. S. Joe Qin, President of Lingnan University

June 2019

HONORS & AWARDS

Graduate Merit Scholarship

Syracuse University

August 2017 – May 2018

Summa Cum Laude Syracuse University

May 2017

May 2017

The Warren Semon Prize Syracuse University

Dean's Leadership Grant

Syracuse University

September 2014

Dean's List

Syracuse University

August 2014 - May 2017

The Founders' Scholarship

Syracuse University

August 2014 – May 2017

**EDUCATION** 

Syracuse University

May 2018

Syracuse University

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science

Master of Science | Computer Science

May 2017

Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Business Strategy, Business Development, Stakeholder Management, Agile Project Management, OKRs, CRISP-DM

Technical Artificial Intelligence, Deep Learning, Transfer Learning, Machine Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling,

Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Monte Carlo, Time Series, Statistical Signal Processing, Data Collection, Data Preprocessing, Data Analysis, Data Wrangling, Data Mining

Tools Amazon SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, R, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Pandas, SciPy, Statsmodels, NumPy,

NLTK, Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog, Atlassian Jira, Azure DevOps